Why did you come back?
I'm wondering.
As soon as I got back I
realized why I had left.
When did you come? Was it two years ago?
Do you know exactly when?
Yeah, October. The last time I worked
was October of whenever, two years
ago. So it's over two years.
And that was?
Superman.
Superman, yeah.
You made a lot of money on that.
Yeah, I think so.
You must have quit for a couple of years.
Yeah.
Did that have any...
Well, it had some very not.
Only in that I didn't particularly
like what I was doing in the film.
Not that the film was bad, but I just didn't...
I just felt that I shouldn't be taking
those kind of films anymore for a while.
So I just decided to stop for a year.
And then I decided to go back to work.
There just wasn't anything
available right away.
What you wanted to do.
When you said you didn't want to do that, you
saw the script of course.
Superman?
Yeah.
Oh yeah, it's one of those things where you
think, yeah, I can make something out of that.
And then you get out there
and then you find yourself
being involved in a big production.
Just being a little cog in a big wheel.
And it isn't a hell of a lot of fun.
Although it may look like it.
The end product may look like fun.
You'd be waiting around pricing crazy.
On a set.
Yeah.
I mean, five, six hours at a time.
Sometimes between setups.
What do you do?
Well, I just started to read,
which I've almost never done.
Once I said I always kind of think
about what I'm going to be doing or
what I'd rather be doing.
Could you have been in the second Superman?
I wasn't.
But they did all mine together.
Oh, that's good.
They did. I worked about seven weeks
and they did both one and two.
At least I think I'm in it. I don't know.
They may cut it out.
Do you have points in the money?
No. So they won't have any reason
to cut it out unless it's bad.
This is also a possibility.
So from October of seventy...
Seventy?
Seventy-seven?
Mm-hmm.
It's almost three years.
Yeah.
It's close to seven years.
So what have you been doing?
I don't know.
I worked two days and one for one.
That's the only thing I can remember.
Really? What's been happening?
Well,
we moved up to Pebble Beach for almost a year.
And I haven't really done
anything constructive.
I read a lot under the
guise that I'm looking for
movie material, you know?
Are you your own production company?
No, really. I don't have a company
that I work out of, but it isn't.
That's the type of thing.
Yeah. It isn't really.
And I have a couple of scripts
under development now.
Ideas that I've had with me jointly
with a couple of people and
we're writing some stories.
I'm not writing them.
I don't have them written.
So the first year you were in Pebble Beach?
Is that it?
Right after that you went up to Pebble Beach?
And what did you do every day? Did you just...
Well, we were working on a house there,
so it kept me busy for a long time.
We had moved into one house and then
we were trying to develop another
house down on the beach.
And it was this wonderful old stone house
that had been there about 60 years.
But it had marble floors,
which were just ice cold, you
know, right next to the beach.
They were clamming.
So I decided I would take
the marble floors out.
And it looks so good without the marble
floors that I decided I would take all
the plaster off the walls and expose the stone.
So one thing led to another
and before long it was
gutted. It was just totally gutted.
It looked beautiful. I mean,
you can see all this wonderful stone, great big
pieces of... ...this very soft
stone that the sea air had kind of
eroded on the outside of the house.
And then the inside was just wonderful.
And then we had plans to put in,
you know, hardwood floors and all that.
Did you do anything yourself, actually?
I did a lot of the demolition.
I was good at that.
That was good therapy. You get in there
with a sledgehammer and take care of it.
You didn't get bored that year?
Not really, no.
Red, cool around with the house?
And I fly a little, you know, kind of stuff.
What do you fly?
What kind of airplanes?
Oh, I've had a number of airplanes.
I've had 20s and, you know,
King Airs and I've had
biplanes, aerobatic stunt planes.
I have a little bonanza right now.
You checked out on it and it's tremendous.
That is a jet?
No, it's a prop jet.
A prop jet, yeah.
How many hours do you have in there?
[...] 1,500.
I guess you and Chris Reeve had a great time.
Yeah, we did.
About six to eight hours every day on the set.
We talked about flying a lot.
As a matter of fact, we flew to Italy once.
Together.
Well,
in that picture you didn't have to fly enough.
Yeah, right.
You're not into gliders, are you?
No, he is.
Yeah, I've done some,
a little bit of soaring, but I'm not checked
out in certain places.
And now you have a bonanza?
Mm-hmm.
And how often do you fly now?
Well, very perversely, I bought it just about
two months before the picture started.
I decided to do a lot of flying.
Now that's strange.
You know, I've flown off and on the
last couple of years, but not a lot.
Flying is kind of a thing where
you get into it and you get
out of it and you get back into it.
The closer we got to doing this picture,
the more I was flying.
I'm sure there's some
psychological reason for that.
You weren't flying the
last time I spoke to you.
Yeah, I've been flying since 64.
Well, you have.
That's when I didn't pay attention.
You're not in the service?
No.
I was doing Hawaii.
And so that was the first year.
Yeah.
And then you came back where?
I came back to Beverly Hills.
Where you have another house?
Yeah, where we bought another house.
Where did you do that?
I don't know.
The time seemed to...
Look, give me an average day
for you in Beverly Hills.
You get up with cars.
I don't think I have an average day.
I don't still live my life like that.
Well, each day is different.
You try to be, yeah.
It's so radically different
when you have no job?
Yeah, I drive around a lot, too.
No, really, just give me a day.
No, I'm telling you, I do.
You drive, you get in your car.
I get my car, I drive around, I think a lot,
and I drive out the beach, I drive
down to San Diego, I drive to Santa Barbara,
out of the desert.
Do you know where you're going
when you get in the car?
You know.
Mm-hmm.
And what are you thinking about?
I guess, you know, just life, heavy.
I don't know if I'm going to
get enough gas to get home.
Well, now, you're independently
wealthy thanks to Superman, right?
Yeah, well, I had money before Superman,
but I've done pretty well.
So, actually, you don't have to come back?
No,
I didn't come back because I needed the money.
Right.
Nor did I come back to, you know, to try to
rekindle any kind of start or anything.
I just, that's really acting as really
the only thing I know how to do well.
And I just thought I would come back to...
Try to atone for some of the
things I had done earlier.
Did this script grab you?
Yeah, it did.
I like the idea of it because the
character changes quite dramatically.
And I go from being, you know,
kind of a fairly uptight, middle management
type guy to looking the way I am now, you know.
You turned down a lot of scripts?
Yeah, I [...]
In that two and a half years,
they constantly threw scripts at you?
No, I don't know constantly, but I would
say we turned down at least ten firm
offers for films.
And I wouldn't even have considered,
you know, three quarters of them.
Maybe there was two in there that
I would have maybe done if I had
a mind to go back to work.
Well, I still don't know what triggered
off your decision to go back to work.
You say there were a couple of
scripts there you might have
liked,
but at that time you weren't prepared for it.
Yeah, well, early on there was a couple
of things that I kind of liked, but I
just really didn't feel like going back.
Then I was offered a lot of adventure
films and that kind of thing.
I felt, well, what's the sense in
coming back to do something like that?
Then this project had been
in the kind of works for the
last nine or ten months.
It was written for me,
and I liked the idea of it.
So it took me that long to get it put together.
You know, when you quit, you made some remarks
critical of this business, haven't you?
Oh, I would imagine, yeah.
And you're one of the top box
office guys when you quit.
You quit really almost on top, would you say?
I don't know.
Your career was, you could have gone on
and you got a big price for your movies.
And yet you just decided
to quit because was it the
Superman thing that triggered it off?
That there was nothing wrong?
I think it was a combination of Superman
and March or Die, which was a film I had
done just prior to that.
I realized that after having done that,
that I was taking films for the money,
not really looking at them that carefully.
And then I knew that it wouldn't
be long before that would be over.
You know, they would just sketch up with you.
So I decided rather than being gradually,
gradually drifting down to things that I
didn't want to do, I would stop and just
put it all aside and see if I couldn't
rekindle some kind of fire in me from the
old days when I really loved
doing what I was doing.
What was that movie you made the
one way to create the wire cap?
That didn't do too much, was it?
All the critics put that very
high among the old classics.
Yeah, I like that work.
You know,
I like that kind of intense kind of work.
I mean, Scarecrow was done about the same time,
and I enjoyed that.
And I...
French, good night, you good?
Yeah.
All kind of vital,
and it has to do with something.
Well, were there scripts like
that coming along after that?
There may have been, but I didn't see them,
or if I saw them, I didn't see them
as being that kind of...
You get seduced very easily in the business.
At least I do.
I did. You know, you find that if you're
brought up in kind of poor circumstances
that it's very easy to justify taking some
big money for something that you know
deep down in you that is
not really great stuff.
Well, now you've made a decision,
are you going to be very choosy?
Not necessarily. I mean, I was choosy
about the first one to come back, but
I don't know.
I think you go through a number of
stages in your life and in your
career about what you do.
Was there things in your private life
that had any difficulties or such?
Oh, yeah. I've had a lot of difficulty
in my private life, and you take
films for a number of reasons.
You know, the location where somebody says,
Morocco, oh, I've never been to Morocco.
I don't think I have to read that script,
you know?
People would be amazed at how many
movies have been done, you know, just
because a guy wants to get out of the house.
And what's your marital status now?
Pretty good.
You're remarried, are you?
But you had problems.
Twenty-four years.
Yeah. There were problems there.
Oh, yeah.
We've had difficulties, but we still care
a great deal about each other.
And we're fairly close,
considering, you know, all the
crap we've gone through.
And you have children. How old are they?
They're 19's boy, Chris.
Elizabeth is 17, and Leslie is 13.
Are either of those children in the business?
No, none of them, they have talked
just on the borders of wanting to,
you know, be in the business,
but none of them really want to work at it.
So I haven't encouraged them. And by work
at it, I mean, they haven't talked in
terms of going to New York and
studying and doing that kind of thing.
So I certainly am not trying
to get them to work just to be
movie people. You know, that's crazy.
What does Chris want to do? Does he know yet?
He's... Yeah, he knows.
That doesn't do with the business.
He wants to race. He races motorcycles,
has been for the last four or five years,
and he's racing go-karts.
He's going to go to England this summer.
Really? How do you feel about it?
I know you're right.
Well, yeah,
I can't very well tell him, you know,
that's stupid because I do it myself.
But I have tried to discourage him.
It's difficult, though.
He wants to achieve something in his life.
And so I don't know if he's going with
my blessing or with my hat on the back
or whatever, but I would prefer
to see him do something else.
But if he's going to do it,
then he has to do it.
He interviewed Larry Wilcox sometime back.
He was in a
race with me that you won, I believe.
But was that the... Not the Jeep thing, was it?
No, that was down at the Long Beach Grand Prix,
a celebrity race down there.
That's right, yeah.
Do you do a lot of that stuff? Yeah.
You were in... Brolin, I guess?
Brolin was in the race, yeah.
I don't know if Clint was in that race or not.
I kind of remember.
Newman was in a race we
did back at Watkins Glen.
What kick do you get out of racing?
Well, it's interesting to...
It has not to do with speed so much.
It has to do with control.
How much control can you have if you
take a car in a certain area that you've
been over 15, 20, 30 times?
It's nothing like that on the freeway,
diving in
and out,
and you don't know what's going to happen.
When you're racing, it has to do with
having gone around the track a number of
times and knowing what gear you're
going to be in and how much braking you
have to do to get through a corner.
The fun of it for me, and maybe different
for other people, is seeing how much
control you have over that vehicle through
a certain corner at a certain speed.
So it's really very skillful.
It has to do with skill as
opposed to courage so much.
You can't be totally chicken,
but you don't need as much
courage as people think you do.
At least at the level I'm doing that.
If you're talking about Indianapolis or
something else, that's something that...
Have you ever thought about Indianapolis?
I was brought up around 80 miles from there. I
saw all the races when I was a kid.
So that's always been kind of a...
I had this mystique about it for me.
I don't want to do it at this age.
No? Is that...
Well, you have to re-skill number one.
It takes years and years to get the kind
of skill, unless you're a young person.
I guess Steve McLean [...]
He was trying to prove something to himself.
To go racing like that at high speeds.
But that has...
Well, it could be. I don't know.
I've never gotten into it that heavily
in terms of...
He was quite good at it.
What's the fastest you've ever gone?
About 160, I suppose.
Have you ever been in a serious accident?
You were a trifle heavier than when I last...
Really?
[...]
Oh, that's nice.
Had to come down here today to tell me that.
Do you really...
Do you think you're at your same weight?
Oh, I have no idea.
No, I'm sure you're... I must have been
doing Poseidon or something like that.
That's fairly thin.
That's right. That's exactly right.
I don't know that I remember it all that.
What did you think of that,
appearing in something like that?
Well, at the time it seemed fine, you know,
because I was just coming off French
Connection, and I had three other pictures
to do afterwards, and it was, you
know, grab it and run, and it seemed okay.
It was the first studio
picture I'd ever...
[...] waiting time.
You know, the first time I'd ever
worked in a studio in the last.
It was interesting.
I didn't think the picture was great,
as far as I was concerned.
It was... It worked on the level
that it was supposed to work.
Well, I'm trying to understand your motivation.
You came back because you now suddenly...
You understand that when you explain it to me.
Well,
I think you're trying to prove something again.
I mean, this is the way I get it,
that you want to become recognized as
a fine actor, rather than a guy who's
just grabbing the money and running.
Well, I don't know about the recognition.
Yeah, you may be right about that.
It goes hand in hand in hand.
Certainly, if you're
doing good work, you're going to be recognized.
It's mostly for myself.
I just... I feel that if I can
do good work and satisfy myself,
that that's all that's really necessary.
Is it tougher for you now to come
back after two and a half years as an
actor who hasn't used it for two years?
No. It comes right back.
It's like bicycle or something?
Is that the same?
Swimming or some of the other things.
It goes right into it. You don't have to do...
I think if I had to go back on stage,
it would be different.
[...]
You know, the Broadway stage.
Because...
It takes some special skills.
What is it that you like about acting?
I guess the concentration.
When you're actually doing it.
The enormous concentration
that really fills you up.
That you can tell when you're doing it right.
You know.
And you get that wonderful feedback from
where that comes from in your body.
In your mind.
That tells you that you're doing
something that's right on.
You feel it with the act.
I guess the real problem with
actors is keeping that mechanism...
honed to the point where you don't
start getting outside stimuli.
Where you...
You then allow that to affect your work.
Whether negative or positive.
That you have to somehow rely on that...
whatever that feeling is.
Was there ever a point where you
thought you might never come back?
Yeah.
Five minutes or so.
No, I go through it every day.
[...] of it.
[...] oh, how?
You think you made a mistake?
What am I doing this for?
[...]
Where you say you made a mistake coming back?
Oh, I don't know.
The regret, I mean.
I don't know.
I don't regret having come back
for this film because much of this
is enjoyable to me.
What would you have done
if you didn't come back?
Say you...
Well, I paint a little and I do some...
I just start working in stone,
which I really love.
Stone?
Yeah, marble.
Sculpting.
Oh, really?
Ideally, I see myself someplace looking
over a meadow with a lot of trees,
looking down to the ocean in the
studio where I am carving stone.
An hour later, I don't know what I'm gonna do.
You want to get in the car and go to San Diego?
Yeah.
I have to drive out to...
But you can afford to do that, right?
City and industry.
You can do that.
You can get up on top of a
hill and do your marble.
You don't have to work.
You say you see yourself.
Yeah, no,
I see myself because I like the idea there.
I like the fantasy of that.
Whether or not I'll ever really do that.
I don't know.
You need something to occupy your mind.
Yeah, I do.
And it wasn't hard for two and a
half years not to work at all.
You didn't do anything?
Well, you know, I've been asked that a lot.
And I could never come up with
any answer other than they.
I read a lot and I've painted
a little and I flew a little.
And outside of that, I can't tell you.
But you didn't work there?
No, well, I worked two days for
Warren Beatty on Reds in London.
Why did you do that?
Oh, just as a favor?
Yeah. No billing, no money.
Did you travel a lot?
Traveled some, you know.
We traveled quite a bit last summer, actually.
Well, what did your wife say?
[...] too home every day.
Good night.
[...] worst one you can think of?
What's the worst one you've ever thought of?
Well, it was kind of a treat, though.
I mean, I've never had a treat for her.
A modesty [...]
Uh, God, because I hadn't been home
for about ten years, you know.
She said, hello.
So you got to know each other?
Yeah.
And your children?
That was a delightful time.
Yeah, it was.
You don't regret that you didn't.
No, no.
That was a good period, though.
Yeah.
You did a lot of heavy thinking.
And now you've got a lot of things resolved.
No.
But I decided that it can't be resolved,
you know.
There are some things that
you just can't resolve.
I guess making a decision, the decision
that this is going to be great working
in movies at this time.
It would be a wrong decision,
because I know it's not going to be
great, but it's all I know how to do.
Are you looking past this picture?
No.
Are you a guy that looks ahead and...
I don't like to look ahead.
One of the most depressing times for me
was when I first came out from New York
after Bonnie and Clyde,
and before it was released.
And the agent out here had lined
up three films for me to do.
I wasn't starting anything there,
but worked for a whole year.
And I found myself up at the Montecito Hotel,
sitting
there waiting, ready to go to work one day.
I was so depressed, I couldn't figure out why.
And I finally figured that I had,
for the previous 15 years in New York, I had
never known more than two weeks'
work in advance at the most.
And doing theater had always been, well,
you're on a five day when you first
start rehearsal on a theater.
They can fire you any time
within the first five
days, and then they have to give you two weeks'
notice.
So I had never known anything other than that,
and I kind of liked it.
You know, living on the brink kind of thing.
I mean, it wasn't terribly dangerous
other than with the job, but I had
been in New York since 1953.
It had been kind of relaxed and easy,
you know, and then I had
this work to look forward to.
And granted, it was things I wanted to do.
I mean, I wanted to act.
It wasn't necessarily great films.
So it's nice not to have more
than one film to do at a time.
Suppose this picture hadn't come along.
Something would have come along, I think.
I mean, you had made a decision,
you were going back.
Yeah. I had decided about eight,
nine months ago that I was time to go
back,
and I started seriously looking for things.
You called your agent and said, yeah.
I'm looking for stuff.
Was there something in particular you wanted?
I had never really told anybody that I
wasn't going to work, that I was finished.
I just said, hey,
I'd like to take some time off.
And people would call every month or so
and say, hey, there's such and such a script.
And I'd say, nah, what do you think?
And they'd say, well,
if you're going to come back for
something, you know,
let's wait and let's hold out.
So it wasn't as if I'd
announced my retirement at all.
I hate those facts that I
retire in every five minutes.
And how did I leave?
There's an office.
Scott's retired at all.
Was there something, especially,
there was some kind of character you wanted?
Well, I wanted to play something
lighter.
I didn't care so much about the character.
I never looked at things for character.
I just wanted to lighten up a little.
I just felt that I was being so heavy and
it was kind of dominating my life that
I ended up...
People thought of me as this kind
of very hard guy or ugly, you know.
I guess that's the better word for it.
And I didn't want to be ugly all the time.
You didn't play any, you have never
played any comedy or anything like that?
Only on Broadway.
Have you any desire to go back to Broadway?
Yeah, I do.
You do want to go back?
Yeah, I do go back.
Can you put that in there so they
can start sending me things?
During the two and a half year hiatus,
whatever we want to call
it, did you ever think of Broadway back then?
Well, what I actually had planned to
do and it didn't work out was, when I
finished Superman,
we had decided to move up to Pebble Beach.
And I wanted to build a theater in Monterey,
or somewhere in that area.
And I found out after getting up there
that there were several theaters and it
was a very tough go because it's a little
touristy in the summertime and not
enough in the wintertime
to keep the theater alive.
And I wanted to do kind of a
repertoire with a permanent company.
I may eventually still do that someday
if I can find a spot to do it.
You know Brent Reynolds?
And you know about his...
Yeah, I was down there a couple months ago.
It's a great place, huh?
Yeah, it works quite well for him too.
The problem with dinner theater though is that
it's kind of a compromise, I think.
It may not be as much a compromise as film is,
but it is some kind of a...
It's got to be commercial.
Yeah,
you have to do commercial projects and many of
them are kind of restatements.
You've maybe already done the project or you...
[...]
And I thought maybe to do some
experimental theater or to do some classic
American classics, Williams and Eugene O'Neill
and that kind of thing would be interesting.
What about... Do you know Barbara Streisand?
Mm-hmm.
Because of the same age?
Yeah.
[...] mean, do you know her well?
Well, I've gotten to know her in
the last couple weeks pretty well.
But before that?
Well, I had not only met her at parties
and once up in Pebble Beach, she was up
years ago when she was at Sue's wedding.
Actually Sue and Joan Claude
were married in Pebble Beach.
So we knew each other a little bit.
And you have never performed before?
No, she doesn't work until next week.
You're looking forward to that.
Yeah.
I can see from the rehearsal that she's
got a lot of juice and a lot of...
It's going to be kind of fun.
That's interesting.
Interesting.
Well, I've asked through the
things that I had on my mind.
And you're going to perform today?
Well, I guess you'd call it that.
Sometimes I come to work and I think,
I'll just walk around today
and not give them too much.
I always try to do the best I can.
I was making a joke about performance,
but some things
are not really a performance.
I mean, because I was just thinking
about what I just did up there.
I just walked through a room.
Well, you could walk through a room and
try to make a performance out of it, but
it might be wrong for the film.
Or you could do something there that
might necessarily not be pertinent.
It might be interesting at
the time and interesting
in the dailies, but it may not be...
Hey, Kevin.
How you doing?
Good to see you.
You going to watch this performer?
Well, I've got to go for a physical.
I'm not the friend of yours, though.
Just recently, shoot it for me.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, he's a hell of an actor.
Have you ever had experience...
I'm doing a separate story.
Have you ever experienced problems
with another actor on the set?
Physical problems?
No,
just where you just couldn't get along or...
Oh, yeah. ...temperamental things and...
Yeah, sure, I think everybody has...
...personnelies or whatever.
Is it very difficult working
on those conditions?
Yeah, I worked with Sandy Dennis
on stage for almost a year.
In the last... ...the middle six months
of that, we never spoke to each other.
I think it would be on stage, yeah.
Which point was that?
Any Wednesday.
And it was just misunderstandings
and things like that.
I often wonder how people can do it.
You know, act... ...things are going
so great and I [...] seeing breaks.
So that is act...
to give the greatest test I can.
We were talking the other day about this.
It has not to do with not getting along,
but in that play, I came... ...went on
one night... with a girl who I had never met.
Sandy had gotten sick at the last minute.
And I guess they forgot to tell me that
she wasn't going to be there, but I came
on about five minutes after the play starts.
And just before I went on stage,
the stage manager said, Oh, by the
way, Sandy's not there.
And I said, Who is it?
And they had just replaced the understudy who I
had worked with a couple of times.
And they said, It's Diane, somebody.
And I went on seeing this person who I
had never seen before, which was okay for
the early part of the play because
I wasn't supposed to know her.
But then like ten minutes later,
half an hour later, we were doing a love scene
on the couch here in this...
Hello!
And the poor thing,
she was just frightened to death.
She had been thrown on at
the last second literally.
Too big fun if you were in a crowd scene,
you didn't know which one she was.
You can choose your own director.
You have that in your contract?
Well,
it depends on how the thing is put together.
Many times, the director is the
first one put into a project.
The more the director finds the project.
But if it's certainly a project of my own,
I would choose my own director.
Well, where have you picked your own director?
Actually, the only time I've ever picked
my own director is John Frankenheimer
in French Connection 2.
Are there certain directors
you would like to work with?
Oh, there's a lot of good directors around now.
[...] piece of good,
fine director, a minister for him.
How important do you think
that is for an actor?
Well, I think it's everything.
It's 75% of filmmaking,
I'd say probably 25% is the story.
[...] Well, really?
I use a piece of meat, and I try to
walk around in front of the camera.
You sound like Hitchcock.
I don't really think that.
The director is probably 40%
in the script, and 40 CAMERON.
And the actors are almost...
I think the actor is only about 20%, really.
But you think so.
You take ten top actors,
and most of them could play the same role.
It's been trained to various degrees
of being accepted depending on their
casting, their body types,
and what they look like.
While you were watching the movies over
the last two and a half years, which I
imagine did, the film,
did you see anything there where you said...
I liked to have been in China Syndrome.
I liked that quite well.
Playing the Douglas part?
No, I couldn't have played that.
Maybe the role Jack Lennon did.
Not that he didn't do it well,
I thought he did it wonderfully well.
There's a number of things that I saw that I
thought, wow, that would have been nice to do.
But all actors see things differently,
so you don't necessarily go to a film
and see, ah, he didn't do it right.
I might have made other choices or something.
Is your attitude now toward this film
the same as it was when you were doing
something like a conversation?
Do you still have that same
drive and that same...
No, I think that that will never be the same.
Yeah, I think that was like
the first and it can never be.
Five-minute warning.
I mean, if you're going to score a touchdown,
you're going to feel cold.
Are we going to...
[...] to a sudden victory.
Yeah, I think that one tends
to expel whatever you have to
offer in maybe ten or fifteen films,
and then there's restatements of things
you've done in various collages of,
you know, ways, trick ways or whatever.
I'm just trying to get about your enthusiasm.
Oh, how high you are.
Business tends to kill a
lot of your enthusiasm.
Well, I mean, does that depend on the project,
though? I mean, to say this...
Well, I think it depends on a lot of things.
It depends a lot on the director.
You know, the director really is the father.
He's the artistic person that you
one should look to.
He's the guiding force in any film.
How about directing yourself? Have you ever...
I think it would be wonderful.
No, not directing yourself,
but have you ever...
No, I've thought a lot about directing.
And I think actors probably fall into the
trap of thinking that directing is maybe
easier than... it actually is, because
you get on the set and you start seeing
things with a fresh eye, where the
director and his people have been involved
in it for nine months, you know, and
they have these ideas, and you come on and say,
Oh, let's move that wall over
there. I feel, you know, you just have
this kind of fresh... And you can't do
that. You just... I mean, the business...
But you make suggestions.
Yeah.
Where you think it could be improved, or...
That's touchy sometimes, isn't it?
Yeah, it gets tricky,
but there again, it depends
on the personality you're working with.
Some directors make you think that the
whole thing is you. It all has to do with
your ideas, and you know, more than
likely that's the one director who has
thought it all out,
and you end up doing exactly what he wants.
But actors are children in many ways, you know.
They just
like to have their own way.
[...] the couple is like that in a way.
I mean, you know that there's really a
strong force there in somebody guiding
this thing, and you're willing and
encouraged to make all kinds of suggestions.
And they kind of all filter in there,
and they all kind of come back in some way.
And you really feel a part of it.
All these actors he's ever worked
with are very loyal to you.
Could you have made a living at
something else that you didn't do?
Oh, yeah, sure. I drove a truck pretty good.
I don't know if I'd ever been successful
at anything that was terribly
regimented, or because I had
terrible difficulty in the service.
I was in for five years and made PFC.
I remember you told me you banged up your knee,
too, didn't you?
Yeah.
I think I've had an operation on it since then.
This is my third operation on the
knee, so it'll never be much good.
Coach, I want to thank you.
Thank you.
These masters, they're all supposed to be...
it's not in our class. They're mass
producing, genuine oil paintings.
Is it?
I don't know.
And there's kind of a story point about it,
since she doesn't want to live in the
loft next to all those Koreans or something.
That sounds a little risky to me,
but I guess there's not that much of
a Korean audience in the United States.
You paint yourself?
A little bit, but I like to sculpt.
Have you sold anything,
or you do just for your own...
I don't know. I've been letting my seat.
What do you mean, salad?
What have you done?
What kind of stuff do you do?
Well, I just started...the first thing
I did was a piece on soap stones, this
kind of green, very soft rock.
[...] kind of a Burmese lady
face with a pair in the hand.
And it was fun.
And then I did my own hand.
[...]
Now I'm doing a...
I bought a 200 block of marble.
And I'm going in to get a face out.
It's that hard work.
Did you take any instruction
you were doing this morning?
Well,
I studied at the Art Students League years ago.
Oh, that's right, sure.
In New York.
See you...
This is your first American movie?
I wouldn't tell it as long ago
before it was a good, awesome [...]
Have you wanted to do one before this?
How about this?
You and Hackman are going
to make a great thing.
A great one line.
[...]
And I think you really need to want
to do it desperately to get it on.
Unless you do...
[...] mean, material is a little different.
I must say I'm lucky because this
project only took two years.
It's been exactly two years to today
that I went to Seattle and I had joined.
It was a fox at that time with an idea.
And then a year left between the idea and
getting a screenwriter and writing it.
Another year to get it on.
Did you see Hackman in the role originally?
Frankly.
We wrote it for...
Except you didn't know it.
Really?
Yeah.
And it just took a chance because in his...
To me, he's probably the best
actor on the screen today.
And certainly in his age group, he has no fear.
Weren't you a little worried that he might
not accept as he had all the other...
He didn't have to roll the dice.
He's been refusing everything.
He refused everything last one hour.
[...]
You really...
I think you have a big chance.
Did you try to persuade him yourself?
No, I said in the script, the fact that
I knew him made it even more awkward.
Because for two weeks he didn't read it.
He was too afraid. He didn't hate it.
I was sweating bullets.
And finally when he read it, like an hour
and a half later he called and said,
and this was even before the
studio had the green light on it.
Then Fox at that time was in kind
of transition and turn more.
So we got him in turn around and...
This is something very different for him.
He's never done anything like that.
I mean it's the first time he's doing...
Light comedy is not really the word.
It's light comedy.
You've seen moments of him
like that in other pictures.
But never throughout.
I'm not sure he can do it.
He's not.
I don't know.
Because he's never been given the
chance to do something like that.
That's good, Bert.
In Broadway you get a lot of comedy.
This is a serial comedy that is based
in reality and it's not straight.
[...]
I think we did Popeye Doyle [...]
That's why I think he's so sick of it.
He just didn't do it.
Is there any French actor that
you would compare him to?
I think it's...
I've seen a lot of French films.
Let me put it this way.
I think he's better than Jean Gavin.
[...] Gavin was wonderful,
but I think he's better than Gavin.
Gavin was much more a sort
of a French Gary Cooper.
He's not as good looking as they are.
He was kind of the quiet.
A lot of present.
Great. It's an extraordinary screen present.
But it was not a great acting.
Jean had a screen present that
happens to be a great acting.
[...] he going to go there?
Is there a favorite Jean Hackman picture?
Do you have a favorite Jean Hackman picture?
I think the conversation is character.
Two pictures that were unfortunate.
They really didn't get there.
Well, they seemed to get the break.
I don't know why they weren't successful.
You know,
whether they were sold right or not sold right.
I don't know.
Or came in the wrong time.
That's possible.
[...] to say, they certainly were rewarded.
And, well,
he won best actor for Scarecrow in Cannes.
And in conversation won best picture.
[...] he won.
You know [...] in Philip.
Yes.
They talk about magic and
chemistry between people.
Well, from the rehearsals I can tell you,
it's really quite extraordinary.
Also, I'm meeting the giants.
They both compliment each other.
[...]
Dream, I keep thinking,
I wake up black and blue in the morning.
So the only person who fucked it up,
they had me.
I don't feel any pressure.
No, no pressure at all.
Oh, that's a good script with people.
That's right.
The only one who can be lousy is the director.
No question about the script.
There's everybody else.
You don't have to glue on each other.
Anything, so that leaves me.
I had the knee of the lab.
The Strider's name starts next week,
is that it?
Officially, yeah.
[...]
W.C.
She's giving a concert on Sunday.
I hope there are benefit concerts at the ACLU.
Is there going to be any music in this part?
There is.
I mean, it wasn't script going on.
The character has a little song she does.
I can't do it to where
we're going to handle it.
This is going to be quite different
because obviously it's not going to be.
It's right [...]
Because otherwise the character
would be distracting.
Because she's not a singer particularly.
[...] has almost hold down.
For that, yeah.
We'll be doing it in a very different way.
Oh yeah.
Because the character has rented
this organ in Yamaha 3000.
Whatever you want to call it.
Five bucks on my friend's.
When you get those basic accompaniments
and things and she kind of writes.
It's just one scene.
But it's really just like he's
an inventor and she kind of has
a vision to hide.
Is it too early to talk about whether
she'll do a theme song for this picture?
I guess it's too early because I don't
think it would kind of be quite right.
Unless we find a very original
way of doing it with the [...]
We have something about
the score of the picture.
It is too early to talk about that.
Especially since she's so new on to the scene.
It's just that I think
she really is playing a
character in this piece.
As soon as you cut it,
if it's not a real comedy
level, the credibility doesn't really matter.
Here the credibility of
the character does matter.
You can't mix two or so
many and nine people up.
You don't want the audience to
see her as Barbara Streisand.
She's playing the character marvelously
and it's kind of the danger of her
singing as Barbara Streisand.
You tend to put the wrong
emphasis in and make you
remember this Streisand as opposed to Carrie.
Are you the right man to ask if the
role has been enlarged for Barbara?
Yeah, it hasn't.
There's no change at all?
We are doing some changes in the third
act which we are planning to do anyway,
which really are more structural
than actually adding.
We are not adding scenes.
In other words, her role isn't being
built up because she's Barbara Streisand.
No, no.
She's really totally fitting into
the picture as the character.
Which I think is the [...]
What is this particular scene
that we are going to see now?
Well, this is the first time.
He starts in a wonderful middle class,
lovely home, open furnace by his wife.
At the end of the picture, he goes back
to a place like this where he starts.
He's almost like two pioneers starting
from scratch, except instead of being out
in the prairie there,
out in the inner city with space and an
uncluttered feeling.
A feeling of going back.
He starts in a super modern,
almost dehumanized corporate
headquarters and ends up in this very
kind of warm and real and full of, let's
say,
certain past where the values were different.
They're going back to perhaps more
old-fashioned values where people really still
have their dreams and try to make them happy.
Forget about the symbolism.
Nobody's going to go and see this picture.
It's fun. It's fun.
Believe me, it's fun.
This is all the stuff.
No, no message.
The message is just, you know, probably there.
Hope that it's not overriding the moment.
I want to thank you.